Guide to the Social Ethics Pamphlet Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Corporate Bodies, Series I
  - I
    - Institute of Religion of the United Church, 1956 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      Comments: Contains "The Supreme Court decision [Brown v. Board of Education]: transcription of statements and debated by Dr. W. C. George, Rev. Charles M. Jones, R. Mayne Albright, and James H. Pou Bailey, at a "town meeting," Feb. 27, 1956.
    - Institute of Social Studies, 1952 (Box 18, Folder 3)
      Comments: The Institute is oriented towards "that group which has faith in the rational examination of social and political problems and a deep suspicion of dogma, mental calcification, obscurantism, and despair." Contains single issue of "Institute of Social Studies Bulletin" (Jan. 1952).
    - Inter-Citizens Committee, Inc., 1961-1965 (Box 18, Folder 5)
      Subjects: Race relations--Alabama; Civil rights
      Comments: Contains dozens of notarized personal statements on human-rights violations against African American citizens, often by the police, in response to the Civil Rights movement. Some documents contain grisly autopsy photographs.
    - Inter-State Narcotic Association, Inc., 1942 (Box 18, Folder 6)
      Subjects: Drug abuse.
      Comments: Contains single issue of "The Narcotic Review" (April 1942).
    - Intercollegiate Association for Study of the Alchohol Problem, 1952 (Box 105, Folder 1)
      Subjects: Alchoholism; Youth
      Comments: contains 4 issues of the International Student, which contains articles about alcholism intervention program related to colleges and universities
    - Intercollegiate Zionist Federation of America, [n.d.] (Box 18, Folder 7)
      Subjects: Antisemitism; Jews; Zionism.
      Comments: Contains "Zionist dream: Israel reality. Part 1: Anti-Semitism. Part 2: Nationalism" [n.d.]; "Program material based on Lewin's 'Self-hatred'" [n.d.].
    - Intercouncil Committee on Christian Family Life, [1948] (Box 18, Folder 8)
      Name changes etc.: Commission on Marriage and the Home
      Comments: Contains "The Christian family in war time" [n.d.]; "Some highlights of the national conference on church and home in a disordered world," prepared by Richard E. Lentz (Nov. 29-30, 1948).
    - Intercultural Education Workshop, [1944-1945] (Box 18, Folder 9)
      Subjects: Education; Race relations; Community organization
      Comments: contains pamphlets issued by the the Workshop which seeks to provide "leadership in positive approaches to racial, religious and cultural conflicts in problems of school and community integration."
    - Interfaith Committee for Peace Action, 1951 (Box 18, Folder 11)
      Subjects: Korean War, 1950-1953; Peace movements
      Comments: Contains "Cables sent by eminent churchmen from abroad to the prayer and vigil meetings held by Interfaith Committee for Peace Action" (Oct. 7, 1951).
    - International Association of Machinists, 1948 (Box 18, Folder 12)
      Comments: Contains "The truth about the Taft-Hartley law and its consequences to the labor movement" (1948).
    - International Association of Universities, 1958 (Box 18, Folder 13)
      Geographical location: Paris, France
      Subjects: Mental health; Universities and colleges.
      Comments: Contains "Student mental health," paper no. 3 of the International Association of Universities (1958). Contents include "What is mental health in a university?" by D. Farnsworth; "The need for an adequate concept of disease in student medicine," by Louis Reik; accounts of mental health problems in Dutch and Mexican universities; accounts of mental health services in British and French universities; and "Recommendations of the Princeton Conference on Student Mental Health."
    - International Christian Leadership, Inc., 1955 (Box 97, Folder 6)
      Subjects: Ecumenical movement; Missions
      Comments: contains newsletters about the group's nationwide activities
    - International Committee on the Christian Approach to the Jews, 1932 (Box 18, Folder 14)
      Geographical location: New York, NY and London
      Subjects: Jews; Antisemitism; Missions to Jews
      Name changes etc.: Associated with International Missionary Council?
      Comments: 15 page newsheet
    - International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, 1949 (Box 18, Folder 15)
      Name changes etc.: ICFTU
      Comments: Contains "For bread, peace and freedom: decisions of the First World Congress of the ICFTU" (Nov.-Dec. 1949).
    - International Council of Religious Education, 1936-1946 (Box 18, Folder 16)
      Subjects: Race relations; Alcoholism; Family.
      Comments: Contains "Value of temperance: youth has no need for alcohol or other stimulants" (1963); "National family week in Christian churches" (May 7-14, 1944); and "Racial segregation in the American Protestant church," by Will W. Alexander (1946); program of annual meeting (1941); pamphlets re. Christian social action.
    - International Labor Defense, 1944-1945 (Box 18, Folder 17)
      Subjects: Armed Forces; Economic policy; Race relations
      Comments: Contains "Army Talk Orientation Fact Sheet" (May 5, 1945): "Prejudice!--Roadblock to progress"; "Cry out, America! For swift justice to end `white supremacy' murders" [1945]; "White justice in Dallas" [in re L. C. Akins], by George Clifton Edwards (Sept. 15, 1945); "FEPC" [1945]; "Legislative Service" (May 1945); letter to President Franklin Roosevelt in re unconditional pardon for Frank Fisher, Jr., and Edward R. Loury (June 10, 1944).
    - International Labour Organization, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      Geographical location: Geneva, Switzerland
      Subjects: International organizations; Labor movement; Technology.
      Name changes etc.: ILO
      Comments: Contains single issue of "ILO News" that surveys the "social impact of technical progress" (1957).
    - International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union--Educational Department, 1938-[1950] (Box 19, Folder 2)
      Subjects: Labor movement; Women.
      Name changes etc.: ILGWU; I.L.G.W.U.
      Comments: Includes papers and pamphlets about the union's program and activites
    - International League for the Rights of Man, 1950-1955 (Box 19, Folder 3)
      Subjects: Civil rights; Korea (South)--Politics and government--1948-1960.
      Comments: Contains letter to "Friends of Michael Scott" in support of the Rev. Michael Scott, an Anglican priest from South Africa, who was seeking a visa for entry into the United States to attend the forthcoming session of the United Nations General Assembly (Sept. 7, 1950); notarized statement of Roger Baldwin, fact sheet, and statement by Emanuel J. Fried in re Chungsoon and Choon Cha Kwak, Korean citizens, who were fighting a deportation order because of their opposition to the government of Syngman Rhee.
    - International Missionary Council, [1947]-1956 (Box 19, Folder 4)
      Geographical location: New York, NY; London, England
      Subjects: Communism; Missions--East Asia. China.
      Comments: Contains two-part memorandum "Professor John C. Bennett's conference on Christianity and Communism" (Feb. 23, 1951; May 2, 1951); "Missionary freedom and the International Missionary Council: a statement by the General Secretary of the Council" [Charles W. Ranson] (April 1950); "The approach to Communism" [Nov. 10, 1947]; single issue of "World Associates Newsletter" (March 1956); "Towards a Christian strategy in East Asia," by Charles W. Ranson (Feb. 23, 1950); "The church in East Asia: Findings of the East Asian Christian Conference held at Bangkok, Thailand, December 3-11, 1949."
    - International Refugee Organization, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      Geographical location: Geneva, Switzerland; Washington, DC
      Subjects: Refugees
      Comments: Contains papers on relocation of displaced persons and the pamphlet "The facts about refugees" (1948).
    - International Religious Liberty Association, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 6)
      Comments: The Association, organized in 1888, teaches "the doctrine of soul liberty" [as described in their "Declaration of Principles"] and "advocates no political or economic theories." Contains single issue of "Liberty: a magazine of religious freedom" (1957).
    - International Solidarity Committee to Aid Labor, Socialist and Democratic Anti-Fascists, 1946 (Box 19, Folder 7)
      Subjects: International relief; Labor movement
      Comments: Contains fundraising letter
    - International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers, AFL-CIO, 1959-[1961] (Box 19, Folder 8)
      Name changes etc.: IUE
      Comments: Contains "The IUE skilled trades program: a reference booklet" (1959); "Resolved: the resolution on skilled trades and apprenticeship training" (Dec. 1960); "Why there is a strike at General Electric: a statement of facts...." [1960]; "On strike at G.E.: Labor's fight on the IUE picket line" [1960]; "Skilled manpower: too little too late?" Two addresses by Rodger Coyne [1961?].
    - International Union of Students, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 8a)
      Geographical location: Brussells, Belgium
      Subjects: College students; International relations; Subversive activities
      Comments: contains papers from the U.S. branch and international branches of this international student organization which was identified as a communist front organization
    - Interracial Fellowship of Greater New York, [1943?]-1945 (Box 19, Folder 10)
      Comments: contains paper and pamphlets issued by the Fellowship which seeks "to provide an opportunity for people of all racial backgrounds to worship together," and "to help the church to become interracial in spirit and in practice."
    - Interseminary Commission for Training for the Rural Ministry, [1940]-1943 (Box 19, Folder 11)
      Subjects: Rural conditions; Theological Education
      Name changes etc.: See also YDSL Record Group No. 47
      Comments: Contains "A study of the smaller denominations," by Wendell Q. Halverson (Union Theological Seminary) (1943); "How the small sect works in the community, from the standpoint of the old-line churches and their leaders," Richard L. Felton, et al (Yale Divinity School) [1943]; "Cultural relations and interpretations," Robert Roy Wright, et al (Yale Divinity School) [1940]; "An analysis of what happens to a community when the sect comes in," by Richard Arnold, et al (Bangor Theological Seminary) (1943); untitled statistical chart [1943].
    - Iowa Christian Rural Fellowship, [1943] (Box 19, Folder 13)
      Geographical location: Dubuque, IA
      Subjects: Rural conditions
      Comments: Contains "The job of the rural church in this day," edited by Calvin Schnucker [1943].
    - Iowa State Teachers College, 1944 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      Geographical location: Cedar Falls, IA
      Name changes etc.: University of Northern Iowa
      Comments: Contains "A proposed statement of an institutional philosophy for Iowa State Teachers College" (April 20, 1944).
    - Israel Information Services, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 3)
      Subjects: Israel-Arab conflicts; Jews
      Comments: Contains "Never have freedom and international morality been so righteously protected," by Abba Eban (June 19, 1967); "The record of aggression: the Arab design for Israel's annihilation" (July 1967).
    - Israel, Government of--Ministry of Religious Affairs, 1950-1957 (Box 20, Folder 2)
      Geographical location: Jerusalem, Israel
      Subjects: Israel; Judaism--Relations--Christianity; Jews
      Comments: Contains "Christians in Israel: a survey," ed. Dr. Ch[aim?]. Wardi (October 1950); single issue of "Christian news from Israel" (December 1957).
    - Israelite House of David as Reorganized by Mary Purnell, [1952-1954] (Box 20, Folder 5)
      Geographical location: Benton Harbor, MI
      Subjects: Sects.
      Comments: Contains pamphlets issued by the sect
  - J
    - James Mullenbach Industrial Institute, 1940-1943 (Box 20, Folder 6)
      Comments: Contains "Towards industrial statesmanship" [n.d.]; "Labor for victory: books, pamphlets and periodicals for workers, labor groups, and labor leaders who are concerned with labor's role in war and peace" (1942); memorandum in re "Pastor's Institute on Industrial Relations" (April 20, 1943); planning memorandum (first page is titled "General objectives") (April 9, 1940); "Memorandum for joint meeting...." [June 1941].
    - Japan Council Against A & H Bombs, 1957 (Box 20, Folder 7)
      Subjects: Nuclear disarmament; Peace movements--Japan.
      Comments: Contains single issue of "No more Hirosimas!" [sic] (March 20, 1957).
    - Japanese Peace Conference, 1951 (Box 20, Folder 9)
      Geographical location: San Francisco
      Subjects: Japan World War, 1939-1945
      Comments: Contains report of conference, address by John Foster Dulles; Constitution of Japan (1947)
    - Jefferson Party, 1952 (Box 20, Folder 10)
      Geographical location: Charlottesville, VA
      Comments: Contains comic book "Crime, corruption & Communism," by M. Philip Copp (1952).
    - Jefferson School of Social Science, 1953 (Box 20, Folder 11)
      Subjects: Communism; Education; Subversive activities.
      Comments: Contains "Why does our government want to close this school?" (May 1953), cover letter (June 12, 1953), and response sheet.
    - Jewish Agricultural Society, Inc., 1941-1950 (Box 20, Folder 12)
      Subjects: Agriculture; Refugees; Jews
      Comments: The Society was founded in 1900 to "assist Jews who are already on farms in the United States and those desiring to settle on farms." Contains "Refugees and farming," by Gabriel Davidson (1941); "Report of the managing director for the period 1900-1949" [1950].
    - Jewish Chautauqua Society, 1954-1955 (Box 20, Folder 13)
      Subjects: Judaism--Relations--Christianity; Jews
      Comments: Contains "Annual catalog, 1954-55."
    - Jewish Frontier Association, [1943?] (Box 20, Folder 14)
      Comments: Contains "The broken pledge: the case against the white paper on Palestine" [1943?].
    - Jewish Labor Committee, [1945]-1952 (Box 20, Folder 15)
      Subjects: Jews Antisemitism; Labor movement; Race relations; Socialism.
      Comments: Contains "Intolerance your greatest enemy" [1945]; "The A.F. of L. fights bigotry!" [1947]; "Tolerance is not enough," by Walter P. Reuther [1947]; "There are no inferior races!" by John Haynes Holmes [1947]; "Organized labor knows the score," by William Green [1947]; seven issues of "The Jewish Labor Bund Bulletin" (1948-1952).
    - Jewish Newsletter, 1952-1960 (Box 20, Folder 16)
      Comments: The "Jewish Newsletter," founded in 1948, is a liberal biweekly review of events and opinion "dedicated to independent thinking and free discussion of Jewish problems." Contains fifteen issues of the "Jewish Newsletter" (1952-60); "A decade of dissent and nonconformity," by William Zukerman [1958].
    - Jewish Statistical Bureau--Public Relations Department, 1958 (Box 20, Folder 17)
      Subjects: Jews; Freedom of religion
      Comments: Contains "The new statistics of religious groups: the principle of equal treatment of religious groups in official records," by H. S. Linfield (April 1958); "Objections to official census records with question of religion" [1958].
    - Jewish Survey, [1942] (Box 20, Folder 18)
      Subjects: Jews; Antisemitism; Subversive activities.
      Comments: Contains cover letter and coupon to Attorney General Francis Biddle in re possible indictment of the Rev. Charles E. Coughlin [a Roman Catholic priest] for seditious activities [1942].
    - Joint Committee for Student Action, 1947-1948 (Box 20, Folder 20)
      Subjects: College students; Catholic Church; Ecumenical movement
      Name changes etc.: Related to International Union of Students, National Student Associations, National Catholic Youth Council
      Comments: Newsletters of the JCSA; "Operation University" - report of student conferences.
    - Joint Conference Committee on Public Relations, ca. 1940s (Box 20, Folder 21)
      Subjects: Freedom of religion; Baptist churches--United States.
      Comments: Contains "The road to the freedom of religion," edited by Rufus W. Weaver [n.d.].
    - Joint Presbyterian Committee on Chaplains and Service Personnel, [ca. 1941-1945] (Box 20, Folder 22)
      Subjects: Armed Forces; Presbyterians
      Comments: Contains "The nation calls the church's youth" [n.d.].
    - Judge Armstrong Foundation, 1948-1950 (Box 20, Folder 24)
      Geographical location: Fort Worth, Texas
      Subjects: Antisemitism; Communism
      Comments: Vituperative antisemitic propaganda.
    - Julius Rosenwald Fund, 1941-1945 (Box 20, Folder 23)
      Subjects: African Americans; Education; Race relations
      Comments: Contains "The Negro: a selected list for school libraries of books by or about the Negro in Africa and America" (1941); "Julius Rosenwald Fund: review for the two-year period, 1940-1942," by Edwin R. Embree (1942); "Directory of agencies in race relations: national, state and local" (1945).
  - K
    - Kaiser Company, Inc.--Child Service Department, [1944] (Box 21, Folder 1)
      Subjects: Child care
      Comments: Contains "Child care problems of the night shift mother" (1944); untitled memorandum publicizing the Kaiser Child Service Centers [1944]; "Designed for 24-hour child care" (1944).
    - Kansai Institute for Workers' Culture and Education, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 2)
      Geographical location: Japan
      Subjects: Education; Labor movement; Japan
      Comments: Contains pamphlet that commemorates opening of the school and describes the curriculum.
    - Keeley Institute, 1951-1954 (Box 21, Folder 3)
      Geographical location: Dwight, IL
      Comments: Contains four issues of "Bulletin of the Keeley Institute" (1951-54).
    - Keep America Out of War Congress, 1938-[1941] (Box 21, Folder 4)
      Geographical location: Boston, MA; New York, NY
      Comments: Contains three antiwar pamphlets.
    - Kiplinger Washington Agency, 1946 (Box 21, Folder 5)
      Comments: Contains single issue of "Kiplinger Washington Letter", "circulated privately to businessmen".
    - Kirkridge, 1949-1959 (Box 109, Folder 1)
      Geographical location: Bangor, PA
      Subjects: Christian communities; Religion and culture
      Comments: contains pamphlets, fundraising letter and review of activities for this Christian retreat and study center
    - Koinonia Farm, 1956-1957 (Box 21, Folder 6)
      Geographical location: Americus, GA
      Subjects: Rural conditions--Georgia. Race relations; Cooperative societies.
      Comments: Contains "History of Koinonia Farm" (1957) and "Newletter No. 8" (1956).
  - L
    - Labor Party of Connecticut, [1938] (Box 21, Folder 7)
      Subjects: Labor movement; Political parties--Connecticut.
      Comments: Contains "Campaign memorandum" [1938].
    - Labor Zionist Organization of America, 1949-1951 (Box 21, Folder 8)
      Subjects: Jews; Israel-Arab conflict; Palestine; Zionism.
      Name changes etc.: Poale Zion
      Comments: Contains "Israel and the American Jewish community," by C. Bezalel Sherman; "Israel among the nations," by Baruch Zuckerman; "What Labor Zionism means to me," by Max Lerner; "Labor's role in Palestine," by Ben Halpern; "Open any door to Israel"; and two issues of "Labor Zionist" (1951).
    - Labor's Non-Partisan League, 1933-1945 (Box 21, Folder 9)
      Comments: Pro-labor pamphlets, newsletters.
    - Laymen's Movement for a Christian World, Inc., 1944-1949, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 10)
      Subjects: Religion and politics; Economic policy; Race relations; Labor movement; Peace movements
      Comments: Newsletter, pamphlets of group dedicated to "build Christianity into the every-day life of the world".
    - Le Tourneau, R.G., 1940-1958 (Box 97, Folder 8,9)
      Geographical location: Taccoa, GA
      Subjects: Evangelicalism; Labor movement; Religion and culture
      Comments: contains pamphlets, newsclippings, issues of the newsletter NOW, issued by the Le Tourneau company--a construction machinery company, which deal with the group's commercial enterprises and its evangelistic activity
    - League for Industrial Democracy, 1932-1962 (Box 21, Folder 11)
      Subjects: Economic policy; Socialism
      Comments: Pamphlets; League "engaged in education toward a social order based on production for use and not for profit"
    - League of Nations Association, Inc.--Education Department, 1930-1933 (Box 21, Folder 12)
      Subjects: International organization; League of Nations.
      Comments: Educational pamphlets re. League of Nations and World Court
    - League of Women Voters, 1928-1954 (Box 21, Folder 13)
      Geographical location: Washington, DC; New York, NY
      Subjects: Citizenship; Economic policy; Subversive activities; Women; Labor movement
      Name changes etc.: National League of Women Voters; Carrie Chapman Catt Memorial Fund, Inc.
      Comments: Includes pamphlets in Freedom Agenda series e.g. "Constitutional Liberty and Seditious Activity";newsletter; "Facts about the League of Women Voters"; "Strikes and the Citizen."
    - League of Women Voters of Connecticut, 1944-1951 (Box 21, Folder 13a)
      Subjects: Citizenship; Education; Economic policy
      Name changes etc.: Connecticut League of Women Voters
      Comments: Includes copies of newsletter "The Connecticut Voter"; informational brochures; one newsletter from the Hamden (CT) League of Women Voters
    - Liberty Lobby, 1964 (Box 21, Folder 14)
      Subjects: Freedom of religion
      Comments: One issue of "Liberty Letter" "Liberty Letter is written to Conservatives who already 'know the score' and want ACTION"
    - Licensed Beverage Industries, Inc.--Women's Division, 1945-1947 (Box 21, Folder 15)
      Comments: Two issues of "Frankly speaking..." - pro-alcohol industry propaganda
    - Lilly Kokomo Project (see University of Chicago)
    - Louisville Council of Churches, 1946-1949 (Box 21, Folder 16)
      Geographical location: Louisville, KY
      Subjects: Church and the world; Gambling
      Comments: Description of programs of Council; pamphlet on gambling
    - Lutheran Research Society, 1946 (Box 21, Folder 17)
      Comments: Newsletters of Lutheran anti-Communist organization
    - Lynn Committee to Abolish Segregation in the Armed Forces, 1957?
      Subjects: Armed Forces; Race relations
      Comments: Leaflet: "Help Fight Jim Crow in Uniform"
  - M
    - Manufacturers Association of Connecticut, Inc., 1946-1948 (Box 21, Folder 20)
      Subjects: Economic policy; Labor movement; Medical care
      Comments: Newsletters" management viewpoint on economic issues. Article: "Compulsory Health Insurance - Good or Bad?"
    - Marble Collegiate Church, 1960 (Box 21, Folder 21)
      Subjects: Religious freedom
      Comments: Letter from Norman Vincent Peale re. his participation in a study conference on religion and freedom
    - March on Washington Movement, 1941-1944 (Box 21, Folder 22)
      Subjects: Civil rights; Race relations; Armed Forces
      Comments: Pamphlets re. Movement, racial discrimination in society and in Armed Forces
    - Maritime Federation of the Pacific--Yanks Are Not Coming Committee, ca. late 1930s (Box 22, Folder 1)
      Comments: Isolationist propaganda pamphlet
    - Massachusetts Mothers' Health Council, 1940 (Box 22, Folder 2)
      Comments: Pro-birth control leaflet: "Labor Looks at Birth Control"; report re. birth control in Massachusetts
    - Mayor's Commission on Juvenile Delinquency, New Haven, 1954-1955 (Box 97, Folder 10)
      Subjects: Juvenile delinquency; New Haven
      Comments: contains 1954-55 report of the commisssion
    - McGraw-Hill Publishing Company, Inc., ca. 1946 (Box 21, Folder 19)
      Comments: Broadside:"The President's Wage-Price Policy Won't Work"
    - Methodist Church, Woman's Division of Christian Service, ca. 1942 (Box 22, Folder 12)